Mabel Thorp Boardman Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Mabel Thorp Boardman Papers 1853-1945 (bulk 1894-1929)
MSS13086
Boardman, Mabel Thorp, 1860-1946
4,000 items
13 containers
5.2 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
American Red Cross official. Correspondence, diaries, genealogical material, letterbooks, newspaper clippings, printed items, and other material relating to Boardman’s career in the American Red Cross and as a commissioner of the District of Columbia.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Boardman, Mabel Thorp, 1860-1946.; Taft, William H. (William Howard), 1857-1930--Correspondence.
Organizations
American Association of the Red Cross.; American National Red Cross.; District of Columbia. Commissioner.
Places
United States--Foreign relations--20th century.; United States--Politics and government--20th century.
Occupations
Administrators.; Businesswomen.
Provenance
The papers of Mabel Thorp Boardman, American National Red Cross leader, were given to the Library of Congress by Florence Keep and Josephine B. Crane in 1947 and by the American National Red Cross in 1954.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Mabel Thorp Boardman are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1861, Oct. 12 Born, Cleveland, Ohio
1901 Member, governing body American Red Cross
1903 1904 Disagreement with Clara Barton resulted in Barton’s resignation from the American Red Cross
1905 Head, American Red Cross, after reorganization Wrote, with John W. Foster, new charter for American Red Cross
1915 Published Under the Red Cross Flag at Home and Abroad. Philadelphia, J. B.Lippincott
1920 Appointed a commissioner, District of Columbia
1921 1944 National secretary, American Red Cross
1922 1939 Director, Office of Volunteer Service (United States)
1944 Retired from American Red Cross
1946, Mar. 17 Died, Washington D.C.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Mabel T. Boardman span the years 1853-1945, with the bulk of the material dated 1894-1929. The collection consists of correspondence, diaries, genealogical material, letterbooks, miscellaneous drafts, newspaper clippings, printed matter, and other material relating to Boardman’s personal life, her work with the American National Red Cross, as a commissioner for the District of Columbia, and in relation to the presidential administrations from William McKinley to Franklin D. Roosevelt. The collection is arranged in three series: Diaries, Correspondence, and Miscellany. Correspondents include William Howard Taft.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in three series:
Diaries, 1882-1902
Correspondence, 1853-1945
Miscellany, 1855-1944
Container List
- Diaries, 1882-1902 (Box 1)
  Diaries.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Diaries, 1882-1902, (18 vols.) (Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1853-1945 (Box 1-11)
  Family and general correspondence and letterbooks.
  - Family correspondence (Box 1)
    - 1853, 1871-1888, (2 folders)
    - 1890, 1930, 1941-1945, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - General correspondence
    - 1877, 1894-1896, (3 folders)
    - 1897-1904, (8 folders) (Box 3)
    - 1905-1909, (5 folders) (Box 4)
    - 1910-1911, (6 folders) (Box 5)
    - 1912-1914, (5 folders) (Box 6)
    - 1914-1915, (4 folders) (Box 7)
    - 1915-1920, (8 folders) (Box 8)
    - 1920, (6 folders) (Box 9)
    - 1921-1937, (18 folders) (Box 10)
    - 1938-1945, (8 folders) (Box 11)
    - "A-W" miscellaneous, undated, (13 folders)
    - Unidentified, undated
    - Letterbooks, 1879-1888, (2 vols.)
- Miscellany, 1855-1944 (Box 12-13)
  Commonplace book, drafts, genealogical material, newspaper clippings, printed matter, and a school notebook.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material and therein chronologically.
  - Commonplace book of poetry, 1878-1882, undated (Box 12)
  - Drafts of letters, addresses, and notes, 1895, 1902, 1920, undated, (2 folders)
  - Genealogy and family notes, 1894-1905, 1920, undated, (2 folders)
  - Newspaper clippings
    - 1882, 1893
    - 1912-1921, 1938, undated, (4 folders) (Box 13)
  - Photographs, 1922, undated
  - Printed matter, 1855, 1891-1894, 1913-1930, 1938, 1944, undated, (3 folders)
  - Sketch books; landscapes, interiors, and people, 1884-1887, undated
  - School notebook, 1876-1877